Today's דף Daf is קנ"ב, Kuf Nun Bet, 152. We pick up
towards the bottom of קנ"א עמוד ב' Kuf Nun Aleph Amud Bet
and we're in the middle of actually pulling together and coming to
some of the general rules about מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shkhiv Meira.
We saw that the משנה Mishna really just distinguished between כל נכסיו
Kol Nekhasav and מקצת נכסיו Miktzas Nekhasav and the הלכה Halakha of
אמר חוזר Amar Khozer or עומד חוזר, Omaid Khozer, אינו חוזר. Eino
Khozer. The גמרא, Gemara, however, introduces other distinctions. It introduces the idea
not found in the משנה, Mishna, but which many people's בני ישיבה
Bnei Yeshiva sort of think is the ironclad rule of שכיב מרע,
Shkhiv Meira, but not in the משנה, Mishna, and it's a חידוש,
Chiddush, not everybody initially is agreed to it, that a שכיב מרע
Shkhiv Meira doesn't need a קנין. Kinyan. דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים
דמי, Divrei Shkhiv Meira Ke-khisuvin Ve-khimsurin Damu, the oral gift is enough.
And the גמרא Gemara also asks, well, maybe is that true also
if it's מתנה במצוה? Matana Be-mitzva? And in the end, it concludes
it's not. Again, that everything that's special about a שכיב מרע Shkhiv
Meira is limited to the case of כל נכסיו. Kol Nekhasav. So
כל נכסיו Kol Nekhasav doesn't need a קנין, Kinyan, מקצת נכסיו Miktzas
Nekhasav does need a קנין. Kinyan. And then the other thing, which
I accidentally just now erased, was this particular piece about חוזר במתנתו,
Khozer Be-matnaso,
במתנתו, Be-matnaso, or דיאטיקי מבטלת דיאטיקי, Diyati-ki Mevateles Diyati-ki, דיאטיקי מבטלת דיאטיקי.
Diyati-ki Mevateles Diyati-ki. That if you are, again, in the special category,
what? If you are in the special category of כל נכסיו Kol
Nekhasav and the special rabbinic institution of שכיב מרע, Shkhiv Meira, so
the same way you have a right to retract if you get
better, or it automatically is voided if you get better, you can
also—a later will can override an earlier one, which is not necessarily
the same thing. Like, this is you only gave it because you
thought you were going to die. Here you do die in the
end, so maybe the first gift should be good. But the גמרא's
Gemara's חידוש Chiddush is that no, the same way, because it's all
in anticipation of the death, you're able to issue a later will
and testament, a last will and testament that voids the earlier will
and testament. So that is another חידוש Chiddush that you can do
that and that also is limited to the classic case of מתנת
שכיב מרע Matnas Shkhiv Meira of כל נכסיו. Kol Nekhasav. And the
other thing that the גמרא Gemara did was it said, actually, now
that we've made this whole major division between כל נכסיו Kol Nekhasav
and מקצת נכסיו, Miktzas Nekhasav, there are cases that מקצת נכסיו Miktzas
Nekhasav also counts as the special הלכה Halakha and that's when it's
מקצת נכסיו Miktzas Nekhasav and you are מצוה מחמת מיתה. Matzaveh Makhmas
Misa. The גמרא's Gemara's example was the woman who said, oh my
God, I'm about to die, and then she gave and then she
gave her gift or whatever and she said what she said. So
when it's explicit, just because somebody's in their deathbed doesn't mean that
they're doing it as a will. Maybe they're just doing business. So
if they're just in their deathbed and it's מקצת נכסיו, Miktzas Nekhasav,
it's a normal ברי Bari approach. But if it's כל נכסיו Kol
Nekhasav or it's explicitly מחמת מיתה, Makhmas Misa, the גמרא Gemara introduced,
that's all these special הלכות Halakhot of שכיב מרע. Shkhiv Meira. Yeah,
but that's what I don't understand, because I thought the whole point
was, like, you know, you would think that the reason why he's
doing this is now, as שכיב מרע, Shkhiv Meira, because he's feeling
מחמת מיתה. Makhmas Misa. So then say that! Because sometimes people are
just doing business. Sometimes a person's in their deathbed for months and
they're still just doing business. We don't translate
everything as—it's okay, so the רבנים Rabbanim made some rules. And once
you actually have מצוה מחמת מיתה, Matzaveh Makhmas Misa, right, you've sort
of solved the problem because, you know, because now if you want
something to be, just go by the rules, but there has to
be—you need some formal rules to distinguish between the categories.
Okay, I mean this is being pointed out now and like we've
been doing this for—I understand. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this:
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיבי רבא לרב
נחמן. Meitivi Rava Le-Rav Nakhman. So רבא Rava challenged רב נחמן. Rav
Nakhman. So now we're in the middle of קנ"א עמוד ב'. Kuf
Nun Aleph Amud Bet. The word starts with the word ובעי קנין.
U-ba-ei Kinyan. Okay, it's like literally halfway down, maybe actually 40% down.
Okay, מתיבי רבא לרב נחמן. Meitivi Rava Le-Rav Nakhman. So רבא Rava
quoted רב נחמן Rav Nakhman as saying that if it's מקצת נכסיו,
Miktzas Nekhasav, it needs a קנין. Kinyan. And he actually rejected, right,
this point. If it's מקצת נכסיו, Miktzas Nekhasav, it needs a קנין.
Kinyan. And he actually rejected those that said that מקצת נכסיו Miktzas
Nekhasav does not need a קנין Kinyan in the name of רב
נחמן. Rav Nakhman. He said don't attribute empty bottles to רב נחמן,
Rav Nakhman, don't say such foolish things. Of course, if it's מקצת
נכסיו, Miktzas Nekhasav, רב נחמן Rav Nakhman said that if it's—that it
does need a קנין. Kinyan. So now that he's established that this
is what רב נחמן Rav Nakhman said, now he's going to challenge
it. Okay? And after he said the other position was foolish, but
still let's see how it works in with the other evidence. So
מתיבי רבא לרב נחמן. Meitivi Rava Le-Rav Nakhman. So רבא Rava challenged
רב נחמן Rav Nakhman this idea that מקצת נכסיו Miktzas Nekhasav needs
a קנין. Kinyan. The משנה Mishna says: שייר קרקע כל שהוא מתנתו
קיימת. Shayer Karka Kol She-hu Matnaso Kayyames. If he's left over little
land, it's valid, right? It's מקצת נכסיו Miktzas Nekhasav even if he
gets better. מאי לאו דלא קנו מיניה? Mai Lav De-lo Kanu Minei?
Aren't we talking about that there wasn't a קנין? Kinyan? Maybe the
same way the case of כל נכסיו Kol Nekhasav didn't need a
קנין, Kinyan, maybe this מקצת נכסיו Miktzas Nekhasav didn't have a קנין
Kinyan and even so it's valid? לא דקנו מיניה. Lo De-kanu Minei.
No, our משנה Mishna is talking that they did a קנין. Kinyan.
So they did a קנין Kinyan with מקצת, Miktzas, they did a
קנין Kinyan with כל. Kol. So with מקצת, Miktzas, it stays valid
and with כל, Kol, if he gets better, it gets voided. Okay,
so the case is they did a קנין Kinyan and מקצת Miktzas
does need a קנין. Kinyan. אי הכי, I Hakhi, says the גמרא,
Gemara, אימא סיפא, Eima Seifa,
let's look at the end, which is exactly what I was talking
about: לא שייר קרקע כל שהוא אין מתנתו קיימת. Lo Shayer Karka
Kol She-hu Ein Matnaso Kayyames.
If he didn't leave over anything, it's not—it's not valid if the
guy gets better, it's voided. At most so he says אי דקנו
מיניה ee dekanu minei if you did a קניין kinyan אמאי אין
מתנתו קיימת amai ein matanaso kayamas why is it not valid because
here the גמרא's Gemara thinking it's so interesting as you see the
גמרא Gemara sort of working this whole thing out. At one stage
we're thinking even below the line is a type of a שכיב
מרע shchiv meira and it doesn't need a קניין kinyan and we're
saying no no no it's on the below the line here with
מקצת mikzas it's totally מתנת בריא matnas bari it needs a קניין.
kinyan. Okay so קניין kinyan means מתנת בריא matnas bari so maybe
even if somebody is in the כל נכסיו kol nechasav category and
he's doing a קניין kinyan maybe he's doing it as a מתנת
בריא matnas bari and not as a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv
meira. Maybe the act of a קניין kinyan defines it as operating
in the
מתנת בריא matnas bari way and therefore עמד חוזר amad chozer right?
That makes sense. So if the משנה Mishnah where it says if
there's a מקצת נכסיו mikzas nechasav remains valid is with a קניין
kinyan then the part that says that כל נכסיו kol nechasav is
voided should also be with a קניין kinyan but wait if it's
with a קניין kinyan why doesn't that make it into a מתנת
בריא? matnas bari? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה amar lei
הכי אמר שמואל hachi amar Shmuel here's what שמואל Shmuel says שכיב
מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים shchiv meira shekasav kol nechasav leachairim once
you're in the כל נכסיו kol nechasav category שכתב
כל נכסיו אף על פי שקנו מידו עמד חוזר shekasav kol nechasav
af al pi shekanu miyado amad chozer even though you did a
קניין kinyan that doesn't put you in the מתנת בריא matnas bari
category once you're in this and it's כל נכסיו kol nechasav or
מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh machmas misa the קניין kinyan does not make
it better or worse. You don't need a קניין kinyan and even
if you do a קניין kinyan you're staying within this framework and
therefore עמד חוזר. amad chozer. Okay that's why I said no קניין
kinyan needed. בידוע שלא היה מצוה אלא מחמת מיתה beyadua shelo haya
metzaveh ella machmas misa once it's כל נכסיו kol nechasav that makes
you doing it because you're anticipating death and therefore עמד חוזר. amad
chozer. Okay so it's very interesting how the גמרא Gemara is like
hey introducing these new ideas that weren't in the משנה Mishnah the
question of the קניין kinyan the question of חוזר במתנתו chozer bematanaso
and then figuring out how they divide at one stage it's suggesting
neither of these need a קניין kinyan then saying no this one
always needs a קניין kinyan okay maybe this one then if it
has a קניין kinyan should be a מתנת בריא matnas bari no
this one is in this category with or without a קניין. kinyan.
So the גמרא's Gemara sort of figuring all that out and now
that's where we've concluded. Wait I just want to get to the
end of this because this is actually a nice little גמרא Gemara
that it sort of pulls it all together in the end. איתיביה
רב מששרשיא לרבא eisivei Rav Mesharsheya le-Rava so מששרשיא Mesharsheya challenged רבא
Rava that this idea of מקצת נכסיו mikzas nechasav needs a קניין
kinyan כל נכסיו kol nechasav with or without. Okay מעשה באמם של
בני רוכל maaseh be-imam shel bnei Rochel there's a story of the
mother of the sons of Rochel Rochel was the father's name or
maybe it means he was a whatever a
merchant yeah whatever maybe his name שהיתה חולה she-haysa chola she was
sick ואמרה ve-amra she said תנתן כבינתי לבתי tinasein kevinnasi le-vitti let
my right let my necklace be given to my daughter והיא בשנים
עשר מנה ve-hi bi-shneim asar maneh and it was a lot very
expensive worth twelve מנה maneh ומתה ve-meisa and she died. For apparent
presumably it was all verbal there was no קניין kinyan וקיימו חכמים
את דבריה ve-kiyyemu chachamim es devareha
and they did it. So you see that even מקצת mikzas it
should work with a verbal מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv meira מקצת
mikzas should also not require a קניין. kinyan. So the גמרא Gemara
says no התם במצוה מחמת מיתה hasam be-metzaveh machmas misa
that was remember we've now introduced a way to get you into
this category even if you're מקצת mikzas if you're explicitly saying I'm
about to die oy I'm about to die I'm afraid I'm about
to die give my necklace to my daughter now you're in this
category now you're in the שכיב מרע shchiv meira category and therefore
it does not need a קניין kinyan and therefore it would also
be עמד חוזר. amad chozer. Okay so because you got מצוה מחמת
מיתה metzaveh machmas misa that's what made that case work in this
category but a מקצת mikzas without an explicit מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh
machmas misa only works in the בריא bari way. Yes listen and
when is even forget about because if you're מקצת mikzas or whatever
but you know there's still מצוה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah le-kayyem divrei
ha-meis. Okay so that you know because you've learned other things but
that's not what the גמרא Gemara here says so I will get
back and talk about that later but that's not relevant right now.
Yes the other one was like don't we also see half the
time בני רוכל צרו עמו bnei Rochel tzarru immo they didn't like
her yeah okay fine you know the rest of this story but
I want to stay focused on what's relevant for us. Yes. Could
you say a little more about who is this שכיב מרע shchiv
meira let's say they start to get a diagnosis that they might
live for two more years right that's a good that's a very
good question meaning I was asking like a more like even even
something more radically different like you know about somebody right like for
example like somebody's about to jump into a fire to try to
save a a you know you know a baby so no I
don't know there clearly they're afraid they might die they're מצוה מחמת
מיתה metzaveh machmas misa but they don't have but they're not dying
right your case is in is even closer to the classic מתנת
שכיב מרע matnas shchiv meira somebody actually has a diagnosis right they
they know they have two years left to live but they're walking
around and they look totally normal and healthy right. Yes exactly they're
not lying down I think that that's an you know an excellent
question I have to do some research on that like what is
because all of these distinctions start with the assumption that the person's
in the bed the person is sick right the גמרא Gemara you
know didn't say deathly ill necessarily you don't know but at least
the person's sick and afraid they might be dying right what if
they're not like laid up right so how. How do you get
into—that's a good question. Let—yeah, go ahead. And I'm saying then that's
the big question. Doesn't matter whether it's partial or all? Well—no, it
does matter if you're not explicit. If you're explicit, the person giving
the bequest and saying, "I am afraid I am going to die.
Here is how I want my property divided," then it doesn't matter.
But if the person just is dividing the property, they're in their
bed and they're saying, "ראובן Reuven should get this, שמעון Shimon should
get that," whatever, then it matters whether it's all or some. Okay.
מצוה מחמת מיתה Mitzvah mechamat mita doesn't mean that we know that
from the context of the fact that you're lying in your bed.
Then everybody would just be in that category. It means you're explicit
about that fact. Okay. Now Michael points out, and I don't want
to get into it, but Michael points out this issue that there's
another principle about מצוה לקיים דברי המת. Mitzvah lekayem divrei hamet. I've
given this example before, which is not the same as מתנת שכיב
מרע. Matnat shechiv mera. מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat shechiv mera was the
thing becomes legally binding. מצוה לקיים דברי המת, Mitzvah lekayem divrei hamet,
like I said, you know, it could sort be like, you know,
it's like when דוד David there says to שלמה, Shlomo, you know,
"Don't let that guy get off free and whatever," שמעי בן גרא,
Shimi ben Gera, the whole thing. Okay, like מצוה לקיים דברי המת
Mitzvah lekayem divrei hamet could be whatever the instructions are, even if
they're instructions about money, okay? You know, "When it's חיים Chaim's birthday,
I want you to give him my Ferrari as his birthday gift,"
right? So he's not giving the Ferrari now. He's wanting his heirs
to do something with his property. So that does not become legally
binding and the property doesn't change hands. That becomes a moral obligation,
you know, on the heirs to do the wishes of the deceased.
Okay, but that's different than saying that it actually, like, took effect
legally. Okay, so that's a different discussion and what cases fall into
that category. Michael said this case about the necklace, maybe it wasn't
because it automatically belonged to the daughter, maybe the sons were just
doing their mother's wishes. Right. So, okay, but you know, but so
that's a separate question which cases would fall into that, but I
want to keep that distinct. That's not our issue right now. It'll
come up. Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Oh, one more question and then we're going to pull it all
together.
איתיבי Eitibi רבינא לרבא: Ravina le-Rava: האומר תנו גט זה לאשתי, Ha'omer
tenu get zeh l'ishti, a person who is like on their deathbed
or maybe deathbed or whatever says, "Give this גט get to my
wife," ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי, u'shtar shichrur zeh l'avdi, "and this writ
of manumission to my slave," ומת, u'met, and then dies, לא יתנו
לאחר מיתה, lo yitnu le'achar mita, don't give it after death because
he's no longer in the position to free his wife or his
slave after he dies. His wife became an אלמנה almanah and his
slave is now owned by his heirs. It's too late for it
to take effect after the person's death.
תנו מנה לראובן ומת, Tenu maneh l'Reuven u'met, however, if he says,
"Give a hundred dollars to ראובן" Reuven and he dies, יתנו לאחר
מיתה, yitnu le'achar mita, give it after death. Now, presumably, there's no
קנין kinyan and nevertheless, you're listening to him.
Okay. וממאי דלא קנה מיניה, U'mimai d'lo kanah mineih, how do you
know there was no קנין kinyan in that scenario? דומיא דגט, Dumya
d'get, the same way by the גט. get. By the גט, get,
the act that would make the גט get effective has not yet
taken place. Okay. And also a קנין kinyan is not meaningful by
a גט, get, right? The קנין kinyan doesn't create the effect of
the גט. get. מה גט לאו בר קנין, Mah get lav bar
kinyan, it's not even relevant to do a קנין. kinyan. אף האי
נמי דלא קנה מיניה, Af hai nami d'lo kanah mineih, they didn't
do a קנין. kinyan. All he did was he just verbally instructed
to give the money to that person and he died, and you
listened to him. Why is it that? That should be a מתנה
במקצת matanah b'miktzat and it's only verbal and it shouldn't be binding.
So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא נמי דמצוה מחמת מיתה. Hacha nami
d'mitzvah mechamat mita. Alright, now we got a good wait, wait to
answer any problem. It's like, you know, it's like the, it's like
the cloak of invincibility or whatever, you know? Anything you throw at
me, I'll just say it's מצוה מחמת מיתה. mitzvah mechamat mita. In
case of מקצת, miktzat, I can solve the problem by saying it's
מצוה מחמת מיתה mitzvah mechamat mita that puts it up into this
category. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara first introduced this idea that it
doesn't need a קנין, kinyan, right? Which it wasn't explicit, but now
we're finding that there's actually a lot of evidence in a lot
of the ברייתות braitot or whatever that it doesn't need a קנין
kinyan and maybe even down here it doesn't need a קנין, kinyan,
and which is the first version of what רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said. But רבא Rava is insisting that רב נחמן Rav Nachman said,
"No, מקצת miktzat does need a קנין." kinyan. All of the evidence
that things that מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera does not is
all the cases either of כל נכסיו kol nechasav or of an
explicit מצוה מחמת מיתה. mitzvah mechamat mita. And now the גמרא Gemara
concludes: רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר מצוה מחמת מיתה בעלמא בעי
קנין. Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua amar mitzvah mechamat mita b'alma ba'ei
kinyan.
So he actually says, "No, no, no. Don't think that מצוה מחמת
מיתה mitzvah mechamat mita allows everything to change." מצוה מחמת מיתה mitzvah
mechamat mita also needs a קנין. kinyan. Okay, maybe it allows, you
know, אמר חוזר, amar chozer, you know, it's interesting, is there anything
that would be a hybrid? Before we said מצוה מחמת מיתה mitzvah
mechamat mita would mean if you stand up it's voided. Maybe that
he's not rejecting, but he is saying it does need a קנין.
kinyan. So what do you do with this case of the give
a hundred dollars? So he says: דתני הני מתניתא במחלק כל נכסיו.
D'tani hani matnita b'machalek kol nechasav. Okay,
that was a case where it wasn't—where he was distributing all of
his property. Either the hundred dollars was everything he owned, or he
said, "Give a hundred dollars to ראובן" Reuven and then he went
on to say what to do with the rest. Okay, so even
though, you know, and you could say that again about... If you're
going to show me a case and you're going to say, "Aha,
look, it was only מקצת נכסים." miktzat nechasim. So I have two
answers. One answer is it was מקצת נכסים miktzat nechasim but it
was מצוה מחמת מיתה. mitzaveh machmat misa. And if I don't believe
in the מצוה מחמת מיתה mitzaveh machmat misa as an answer, I'll
say that was a case where that was the only thing the
person owned, or even if they owned more stuff, they gave that
away while they were giving away everything else. So in the context
of giving away everything, it's כל נכסיו. kol nechasav. Okay, so that's
the way we get out of those issues. But you obviously see
that it's not so black and white. There's reason to think that
even in this מצוה mitzaveh category, it should be you don't need
a קנין, kinyan, but this is still how the גמרא Gemara clearly
wants to be ending up with this big line between the two,
and this is what the גמרא Gemara now says at the end.
Wait, wait, I got to read the conclusion. We have clear-cut הלכתא,
hilchata, Michael who's going to be very, very happy. Okay, במחלק כל
נכסיו דהיא מתנת שכיב מרע שויה? b'mechaleik kol nechasav d'hi matnas shchiv
mera shavya? That turns it into a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv
mera of part of everything being distributed. והלכתא, v'hilchata, and the הלכה
halacha is מתנת שכיב מרע במקצת בעי קנין, matnas shchiv mera b'miktzat
bei kinyan, which is what we were just now debating. If it
is מקצת, miktzat, it does need a
קנין, kinyan, even though he dies, it's not a case of עמד
amad or whatever, he dies and therefore it's all the more reason
to think that it should be valid. No. If it didn't have
a קנין, kinyan, it doesn't work. If it's מקצת miktzat and you're
not explicitly מצוה מחמת מיתה, mitzaveh machmat misa, it is only working
like a normal מתנת ברי. matnas bari. Okay, so I don't care
if he lives, if he dies, whatever, if you didn't have a
קנין, kinyan, it does not work. Okay. So if there is a
קנין kinyan and then he gets better, then it's still valid. Then
עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. You were saying it's like מתנת
ברי. matnas bari. Exactly. Okay, we're just making, all right, we're just
making it very clear. You, for you that would have been clear.
But anyway, מקצת miktzat only works as מתנת ברי, matnas bari, you
always need a קנין, kinyan, and whether he dies or not, it
remains valid. מצוה מחמת מיתה, mitzaveh machmat misa, however, if you're up
here, if you're either כל נכסיו kol nechasav or מצוה מחמת מיתה,
mitzaveh machmat misa, right, which we're now saying is completely like כל
נכסיו kol nechasav that we were discussing, but this is how we're
concluding, okay, לא בעי קנין lo bei kinyan does not need a
קנין, kinyan, and he dies, but it would only be effective if
the guy died. Okay, עמד חוזר, amad chozer, but if he gets
better, right, that's the other thing that's true about a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shchiv mera, if he gets better it does get reversed
ואף על גב דקנו מיניה, v'af al gav d'kanu minei, even with
a קנין. kinyan. Okay, that's the other thing we said. Once you're
on this top line, you're either כל נכסיו kol nechasav or you're
מצוה מחמת מיתה, mitzaveh machmat misa, you don't need a קנין, kinyan,
but a קנין kinyan doesn't make it any different. A קנין kinyan
doesn't turn it into a מתנת ברי. matnas bari. Once you're on
this line, it's always a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mera with
or without a קנין kinyan it's going to be effective, with or
without a קנין, kinyan, עמד חוזר amad chozer if the guy gets
better it gets voided. So don't think the קנין kinyan prevents it
from being voided. Okay. So if he goes through the step of
making a קנין, kinyan, aren't you trying to like, so the גמרא's
Gemara going to deal with that, maybe why did you do a
קנין kinyan if you didn't need to? So maybe just to emphasize,
to make it unambiguous, but the גמרא's Gemara going to deal with
in a second the possibility that in some circumstances the point of
a קנין kinyan might be to say עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino
chozer. Okay, but let's start with the baseline, which is once you're
in this category, it's all because you're assuming you're going to die.
So therefore עמד חוזר, amad chozer, therefore you can void it, a
קנין kinyan doesn't change its nature. When you're down here, we assume
that it is not a שכיב מרע shchiv mera thing, it requires
a קנין, kinyan, because it's not a שכיב מרע shchiv mera thing,
even if it's עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. Yes. Something I
don't understand about the comparison. I wouldn't have compared a גט, get,
explicitly it's not a בר קנין, bar kinyan, and the money is
a בר קנין, bar kinyan, I don't understand how, it's just saying
that since the, that it would be very hard to introduce into
that ברייתא braisa that the reason when he says give a hundred
dollars to my kid, it works, is because he did a קנין
kinyan on the hundred dollars. The whole context of the ברייתא braisa
is all he had was his verbal instruction and he didn't do
anything else. And therefore by the גט get we can't carry it
out, but by the gift we can. It's just saying that it
would be bizarre to introduce and to make a claim that that
was a case of a קנין. kinyan. Okay. All right, so now,
now it seems like we've got everything figured out. Like we certainly
see that there were different possibilities, but we've got it all figured
out, and now we're going to once again complicate it. Now, I'm
going to read this next section like the תוספות Tosafot because the
רשב"ם Rashbam reads it in a way that completely throws everything back
here into disarray, so I'm not, I'm going to ignore the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, I'm going to be תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, let's take a look.
איתמר, itamar, it was taught. מתנת שכיב מרע שכתב בה קנין. matnas
shchiv mera she-kasav bah kinyan. Okay, it was a מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnas shchiv mera, but it was specifically with a שטר, shtar, and
the fact that a קנין kinyan was done was written in the
שטר. shtar. Although we said a קנין kinyan here does not affect
this הלכה halacha and
עמד חוזר, amad chozer, maybe a קנין kinyan means you want it
to be valid even regardless. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, well,
that could be possible if you did two things. You wrote a
שטר, shtar, okay, and maybe a שטר shtar makes you say you
want it to be valid עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino chozer, or
no, a שטר shtar is just because you want it to be
clear and unambiguous, you want your instructions to be, you know, very
precise and remembered. But let's say you did both. You did a
שטר shtar and you did a קנין, kinyan, and not only did
you do both, in the שטר shtar you wrote, "And they acquired
from him," like you know how in a כתובה k'suva it
says וקנינא מיניה, v'kanina minei, you know, באומנא דכשר למקניא ביה ובכל
שאר וקיים? b'umana d'kasher l'miknya beih u-v'chol shear va-kayam? Right? In the
שטר shtar it says, the שכיב מרע shchiv mera said so and
so and we did a קנין. kinyan. on behalf of the recipients
and it says that in the שטר. shtar. Maybe that is said
to really make it binding regardless, okay? The reason the רשב"ם Rashbam
throws it all in disarray is that the רשב"ם Rashbam says that
this is the גמרא'ס Gemara's question is even without a שטר, shtar,
even just the fact that you did a קנין, kinyan, which basically
goes back and reopens all the other earlier discussion, right? But the
תוספות Tosafos no no no, if we've already decided if you did
a קנין kinyan by itself it doesn't make a difference. Okay, עמד
חוזר. amad chozer. What we want to know is not just you
did a קנין kinyan but you wrote it in a שטר. shtar.
The fact that you did a קנין kinyan and you wrote it
in the שטר, shtar, exactly. So you do all three of these?
Correct. Correct, then we're just in our normal rule. This applies even
if it's written, that's a דייתיקי, dayatiki, right? So it's a דייתיקי
dayatiki מבטל דייתיקי. mevatel dayatiki. עמד חוזר, amad chozer, you can reverse
another will. So just a just a written will by itself does
not have more power than this line, just a קנין kinyan does
not change these realities, but what if you had a will with
a קנין, kinyan, okay, but it doesn't, and it's explicitly written in.
That the גמרא Gemara said maybe we should rethink whether עמד חוזר.
amad chozer. So that's the question. Does it mean קנין סודר? kinyan
sudar? Well we're talking about סודר, sudar, okay, but whatever, let's take
a look. איתמר, Itmar, מתנת שכיב מרע שכתב בה קנין. matnas shchivmera
shekasav bah kinyan. בי רב משמיה דרבא אמרי, Bei Rav mishmeih deRava
amri, the house of רבא, Rava, the ישיבה yeshiva of רבא, Rava,
they said in the name of רבא, Rava, ארכביה אתרי רכשי. arkvei
atei richshei. It's riding on two chariots. Okay, meaning it's sort of
it's it's like it's in both categories. Of course if the two
chariots are going in opposite directions you got a problem. ושמואל אמר,
Ushmuel amar, what does that mean? We're going the גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to explain it. ושמואל אמר: Ushmuel amar: לא ידענא מאי אדון בה.
lo yadana mai adun bah. I don't know because it's it's this
hybrid, I don't know what הלכתי halachic status to give it. Okay,
בי רב משמיה דרבא אמרי: Bei Rav mishmeih deRava amri: ארכביה אתרי
רכשי, arkvei atei richshei, it's in two chariots. הרי היא כמתנת ברי.
Harei hi kematnas bari. On the one hand because it has a
קנין kinyan and a שטר shtar and it's written in the שטר,
shtar, all of that, that's giving a weight like a מתנת ברי,
matnas bari, and והרי היא כמתנת שכיב מרע. viharei hi kematnas shchivmera.
On the other hand it's כל נכסיו kol nechasav and a classic
שכיב מרע shchivmera would even say, you know, כד קציר ורמי בערסיה
kad kashiv urami barseih as the guy was sick and lying in
his bed. So you're describing it, the circumstances are such and it's
how it's even being described explicitly as a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas
shchivmera and at the same time it's done with all the trappings
of a classic מתנת ברי, matnas bari, a שטר shtar with a
קנין kinyan explicitly stated. So what are we going to throw so
what how are we going to give it like treat it הלכתית?
halachically?
So,
so הרי היא כמתנת ברי שאם עמד אינו חוזר. harei hi kematnas
bari she'im amad eino chozer. So because of that extra weight we're
going to say it's going to remain binding even if the person
gets better. עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino chozer, okay? הרי היא כמתנת
שכיב מרע, Harei hi kematnas shchivmera, but it still works as a
מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchivmera. Now why do you need it to
work as a מתנת שכיב מרע? matnas shchivmera? Okay, you already have
a you already have an effective קנין, kinyan, you're saying עמד אינו
חוזר, amad eino chozer, what why should it work? Well one thing
you could say is which the which is, would you be able
to have another will and testament to void it? But presumably we
know the answer. The answer would be no. The גמרא Gemara says
anything that אם עמד חוזר חוזר במתנתו. im amad chozer, chozer bamatnaso.
Once we're saying עמד אינו חוזר amad eino chozer that it can't
be voided at this stage, if you get better then you can't
override it with another will. So then what what's left for being
a דברי שכיב מרע? divrei shchivmera? It's just a straight מתנת ברי.
matnas bari. Here's the way it's valuable as a מתנת שכיב מרע.
matnas shchivmera. Okay, הרי היא כמתנת שכיב מרע שאם אמר הבוטי לפלוני
הבוטי לפלוני, harei hi kematnas shchivmera she'im amar havata leploni, havata leploni,
that you can do things with a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchivmera
you can't do with a normal קנין. kinyan. You can transfer a
debt. Right, remember we had that discussion transferring a שטר חוב, shtar
chov, even transferring a debt. How do I if Michael owes me
a hundred dollars, how do I transfer it to Eli? There's no
way unless I get Michael and Eli in the same room at
the same time and I do a מעמד שלשתן. ma'amad shlashtan. But
without a מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shlashtan I have no way of transferring
an abstract debt. As if it's a שטר shtar I could transfer
to Eli, but then I could still be מוחל mochel the debt.
If a שכיב מרע shchivmera however transfers the debt to Eli then
number one it doesn't need מעמד שלשתן, ma'amad shlashtan, something this is
no way to do with normal קניינים kinyanim without מעמד שלשתן. ma'amad
shlashtan. No he just says that money that that Michael owes me
now now he owes it to Eli. I'm transferring that debt to
Eli. So it doesn't need any any מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shlashtan it
would without a מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shlashtan no other קנין kinyan would
work but שכיב מרע shchivmera works and based on שמואל'ס Shmuel's teaching
earlier if it was a שטר shtar whatever, the person and the
heirs cannot be מוחל mochel it anymore. It's directly owed to Eli.
It's not going through, you know, the original creditor. So that way
it still has power that is only for a מתנת שכיב מרע.
matnas shchivmera. Okay, I mean it's limited, it could be huge if
the guy has millions of outstanding debts, it's a it's a huge
power, but it is interesting that it's only in that like one
area that it works on debt. Basically though once you have a
שטר shtar with a קנין kinyan it has it's עמד אינו חוזר,
amad eino chozer, you cannot retract it, but it still is has
power, it has the of a of a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas
shchivmera for this הלכה. halacha. That's what רב Rav says. ושמואל אמר,
Ushmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says, לא ידענא מאי אדון בה, lo yadana
mai adun bah, I don't know how to treat it. שמא לא
גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר, shema lo gamar lehaknos'o ela beshtar,
maybe because he did all of this to indicate that it was
like a normal קנין. kinyan. Maybe he only wanted it to work
as a שטר. shtar. Okay, but if he only wanted it to
work as a שטר, shtar, then fine, let it just be a
מתנת בריא, matnas bari, end of day, you know, go home. What's
the big deal? No, maybe if you only wanted it to work
as a שטר, shtar, you're now it's the worst of both things.
Why would it be the worst of both things? Because אין שטר
לאחר מיתה, ein shtar l'achar misa,
there's no שטר shtar after death. Now, what does that mean? Okay,
there's no שטר shtar after death. But did he not give him
the שטר shtar yet? So you could read this two ways. You
could read it that we're assuming that he wrote it in the
שטר shtar and the שטר shtar hadn't been handed over yet. That
sort of would space parallel to the אין גט לאחר מיתה ein
get l'achar misa that we said before. But the רשב"ם Rashbam says
and תוספות Tosfos doesn't seem to argue that no, even if the
שטר shtar was handed over to the recipient, since in the guy's
mind, he wants it to be effective as a will. So if
he wants it to be effective as a will, when does he
want it to take effect? After he dies. So on the one
hand, he's doing everything to make it with the
mechanisms of a classic מתנת בריא, matnas bari, but he wants it
to take effect at the time that a will takes effect after
he dies. So then he gets nothing. It has zero effect. Because
if you want a מתנת בריא matnas bari to take effect after
death, it can't take effect after death. Anything that you do, if
you're not working within a special שכיב מרע shchiv me-ra category, any
normal gift you give. If I right now said to Eli, I
want you to own my Ferrari after I die, after a hundred
and twenty years, or whatever, even if the Ferrari were still around,
he wouldn't own it, because at that time I'd be dead, and
I can't affect a transfer after death. Okay, so what שמואל Shmuel
says, it's the worst of both worlds. He's giving it all of
this strength to make it like a powerful מתנת בריא, matnas bari,
okay, but rather than saying it's that, it has the benefit of
that and the benefit of a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv me-ra,
we say the opposite. It's a מתנת בריא matnas bari that's trying
to operate like a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv me-ra and take
effect after death. And therefore it's completely ineffective. Okay, so that's what
שמואל Shmuel says. So for רב, Rav, it's basically like a beefed
up מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv me-ra. It's a מתנת שכיב מרע
matnas shchiv me-ra and you know it's a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas
shchiv me-ra because it works on loans and it works on those
things, but it's beefed up and it says this is a מתנת
שכיב מרע matnas shchiv me-ra that I am revoking any right I
have to retract it. Okay, that it's going to take effect regardless.
But it's still a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv me-ra, but a
beefed up one. For שמואל, Shmuel, it's basically a מתנת בריא matnas
bari that you want to operate like a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas
shchiv me-ra and take effect after death, and it can't work then,
so nothing happens. Okay, so that's the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel. Yeah, so this basically has to do with estate planning,
right? Only time you can't do anything in advance really, is that
what this is saying? You can't do anything, well, that's your general
question that we had all along, which is if you wanted to
do it and you didn't want to wait to the last minute
when you were in your deathbed, how do you do it like
ahead of time, right?
So you know, I mean you could so that's first of all,
yeah, but a will to work לאחר מיתה l'achar misa right, would
only work if the person was in their שכיב מרע shchiv me-ra
category, right? A דייתיקי diayteki wouldn't right. So you could either do
it and you could that's partly my question on מצוה מחמת מיתה,
m'tzaveh machmas misa, right, let's say somebody when they were nice and
twenty years old basically wrote up a will and said, and maybe
they said explicitly בשטרא, bishtar, I am saying this because of my
anticipating my death, whenever that should happen, עד סוף מאה ועשרים, ad
sof meah v'esrim, right, would that make it like מצוה מחמת מיתה
m'tzaveh machmas misa and put it into this category? I don't know,
I mean that's a really good question, but you're right, like it's
crazy, we don't want somebody to have to wait to the last
minute to have to do this. Yeah, I have to find out
like if there's other ways to get yourself into this
category if you're not lying in your deathbed. Right. Exactly. Or you
could say I want it to take effect the second before I
die, but then it doesn't include all of the property
that you earned or whatever from that point onwards. So that's why,
right, it's hard
to do it in the most effective way. That is correct. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: שמא לא גמר לאקנויה
אלא בשטרא ואין שטר לאחר מיתה. shema lo gamar l'aknosah ela bishtar
v'ein shtar l'achar misa. ורמי דרב אדרב ודשמואל אדשמואל. v'rami d'Rav a-d'Rav
v'd'Shmuel a-d'Shmuel. Now we show a contradiction of רב Rav against רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel against שמואל. Shmuel. דשלח רבין בשמיה דרבי אבהו,
d'shalach Rabin b'shmei d'Rabbi Abbahu, רבין Rabin sent in the name of
רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, הוי ידועי, hevei yadu'i, you should know, דשלח
רבי אלעזר לגולה, d'shalach Rabbi Elazar l'Golah, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar sent
to the exile, to בבל, Bavel, משום רבינו, mishum rabbeinu, in the
name of our master.
Who was his master?
Oh, that's רב. Rav. רב. Rav. In the name of רב. Rav.
שכיב מרע שאמר כתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני ומת, shchiv me-ra she-amar kisvu
u-snu maneh l'ploni u-meis, a שכיב מרע shchiv me-ra says, write and
give a hundred dollars to so-and-so and then he died, without it
having actually been done, אין כותבין ונותנין, ein kosvin v'nosnin, you don't
do it, שמא לא גמר לאקנויה אלא בשטרא ואין שטר לאחר מיתה,
shema lo gamar l'aknosah ela bishtar v'ein shtar l'achar misa, maybe he
only wanted it to take effect with the שטר shtar and the
שטר shtar doesn't take effect לאחר מיתה. l'achar misa. Now in this
case, the שטר shtar itself wasn't even given till after death, so
that's even a more classic אין שטר לאחר מיתה, ein shtar l'achar
misa, right, the שטר shtar can't be given after death because the
guy's already dead. Okay, but the point is that because he incorporated
an idea of a שטר, shtar, we say that that's not adding
strength to a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv me-ra, it's changing the
nature, and maybe it's only going to take effect in the context
in which the שטר shtar takes effect. So that's רב. Rav. But
רב Rav before said a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat Sh'chiv Mera with
a שטר Shtar and a קניין Kinyan is a stronger מתנת שכיב
מרע, Matnat Sh'chiv Mera, right? And here it's saying it only works
like a שטר Shtar and it made and without the שטר Shtar
having been given, it won't take effect. Is a קניין Kinyan also
true? You mean if it was only a שטר Shtar and not
a קניין, Kinyan, so maybe that would maybe that would, yeah, that'd
be funnier. But then it would like cause all those things are
seen as just strengthening a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnat Sh'chiv Mera. So
how exactly that mix would change its category would be strange, but
maybe you could have said that. Okay, ואמר רב, Ve'amar Rav, so
that's רב, Rav, so רב Rav seems to be switching sides, saying
once you do something within the context of a שטר, Shtar, it's
going to work only later like a שטר, Shtar, okay, and not
like a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnat Sh'chiv Mera. ואמר רב יהודה משמואל,
Ve'amar Rav Yehuda mi'Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel says הלכתא Hilchata he disagrees
and says כתבו ותנו, Ketvunu u'tnu, that you actually do give it,
even to give the שטר Shtar אחר מיתה, Achar mitha, even though
שמואל Shmuel said earlier that with a שטר Shtar and a קניין
Kinyan and maybe even if the שטר Shtar was handed over, it's
not effective. So here they ממש Mamash seem to be reversing themselves.
Before with a קניין שטר Kinyan Shtar רב Rav made it better
and שמואל Shmuel made it worse, and here it's like the opposite.
So what's the answer? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says קשיא דרב אדרב קשיא דשמואל אדשמואל, Kashya de'Rav
ad'Rav kashya de'Shmuel ad'Shmuel, seems like they're contradicting themselves in both ways.
דרב אדרב לא קשיא. De'Rav ad'Rav lo kashya. Now רב Rav is
not contradicting himself. הא דקנו מיניה הא דלא קנו מיניה. Ha diknu
minei ha de'lo kanu minei. Look at that Eli, you're מכוון. Mechaven.
Okay, so did you do a קניין Kinyan or did you not
do a קניין? Kinyan? So he like picked that up. When we
said the case about when he says כתבו ותנו, Ketvunu u'tnu, it's
different to say that you did a קניין. Kinyan. Okay, so somehow
here it's some interesting combination that when you did a קניין Kinyan
plus a שטר Shtar and you wrote the שטר. Shtar. Now that's
one way to read, I'll tell you sort of how תוספות Tosafot
reads it in a minute. Okay, the way but one way to
read it is you just the very fact that you did not
actually in fact do a קניין. Kinyan. So in the first case
you did a קניין, Kinyan, you did a שטר, Shtar, you wrote
the קניין Kinyan in the שטר Shtar etc. That makes it a
strong מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat Sh'chiv Mera
and takes effect
just
but in
a way that you can't be חוזר. Chozer. The writing of the
fact of the קניין Kinyan in the שטר Shtar makes you unable
to retract. Okay, whereas in the other case since it wasn't written
in the שטר, Shtar, it doesn't have that power. Now even if
it doesn't have that power, okay, you could still ask the question
about like, okay, but why can't it just work like a normal
מתנת שכיב מרע? Matnat Sh'chiv Mera? Why can't it be binding? Why
do we say לא גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר ואין שטר אחר מיתה?
Lo gamar lehaknoto ela beshtar ve'ein shtar achar mitha? But that's already
possible. You might remember we had this discussion before, right? That you
remember for example, I'll give you something to help you sort of
refresh your memory on this. I mean this it gets very confusing,
but I'll just remember the case of the משנה Mishnah was a
person that was found with a דיאטיקי קשורה על מתנו, Diatiki keshura
al matno, like a will on their side and they had written
the whole will and nevertheless it was not effective because it hadn't
been handed over.
You remember that? שטר זה. Shtar zeh. Now even though he'd just
said the words in the שטר, Shtar, he just verbalized them without
writing it, it would have been effective as a מתנת שכיב מרע.
Matnat Sh'chiv Mera. Because he wrote it as a שטר, Shtar, okay,
then it means that he only maybe wants it to be effective
in the שטר Shtar approach, which is by the giving over of
it, not by the verbalizing of it. And then the question would
be what if he verbalized it and wrote it as a שטר?
Shtar? Does he do we say that it doesn't take effect until
the שטר Shtar is handed over? So that's this case. This case
was he said write a שטר Shtar and give it to somebody.
So even if it's totally working within מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnat Sh'chiv
Mera, this is דיאטיקי. Diatiki. Which part which like, you know, which
path of מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat Sh'chiv Mera do you want to
operate on? The verbal path, which will take effect right away, or
the שטר Shtar path, which will only be binding once the שטר
Shtar is handed over. So רב Rav says if the guy says
give it in writing, he's on the שטר Shtar path of מתנת
שכיב מרע, Matnat Sh'chiv Mera, and if it wasn't given before the
guy dies, it's not binding. That's the case of the latter case
we quoted. The earlier case was that first of all the earlier
case might that the שטר shtar was handed over, number one, that
wasn't clear. The earlier case might very well be that the שטר
shtar was handed over. But number two, somehow it's the combination of
the קנין kinyan and the שטר shtar and the קנין kinyan being
written in the שטר shtar that makes it clear that we want
it to be as effective as possible. So there, it takes effect
regardless and the person can't be חוזר. chozer. Yes. First of all,
it's extremely clarifying to me. It's now, it's so obvious, like the
power of a שטר shtar is only effective once it's handed
over. There's a מסירה, mesirah, just the writing of a שטר. shtar.
So, so let's take
a כתובת אשה. kesubas isha. No,
no, that's not true. So the שטר, shtar, there's two types of
שטר: shtar: there's a שטר ראיה shtar ra'ayah and a שטר קנין.
shtar kinyan. A שטר shtar that effects, that's an instrument of transfer,
takes effect basically like when it's handed over. A שטר shtar that
is a שטר ראיה, shtar ra'ayah, which is what a כתובת אשה
kesubas isha is, that just proves events that took place but is
not the actual instrument. The actual instrument was the קנין. kinyan. So
that, right, so that does, that does not need to be handed.
You don't really have to give it to her under the חופה?
chuppah? Well, a שטר shtar is only, you do not have to
give it to her under the חופה, chuppah, and this whole idea
that they have nowadays that you need עדים aidim to see the
handing over of a שטר shtar under the חופה, chuppah, that's like
I don't know where that came from. Okay, basically, but it only
serves as a ראיה ra'ayah once it's in her hands, but it's
not a part of the, the effect of it was through the
קנין, kinyan, not through the שטר. shtar. Okay, that's שטר ראיה. shtar
ra'ayah. We're dealing here with more like a שטר קנין. shtar kinyan.
It was a good question. It gave me an opportunity to clarify
that, but I want to get back. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says
like this. So anyway, the answer for רב Rav is,
if you just say do it through a שטר, shtar, then it's
a שכיב מרע shechiv mera with the שטר shtar path, and the
שטר shtar has to be handed over. But if it's a combination
of a קנין kinyan and a שטר shtar and the קנין kinyan
was written in the שטר, shtar, then it is a beefed up
normal שכיב מרע shechiv mera and therefore can't be חוזר chozer and
so on. That's רב. Rav. דשמואל דשמואל לא קשיא. De-Shmuel de-Shmuel lo
kashya. שמואל Shmuel does not contradict himself. ביפה כחו. Bi-meyafes kocho. When
you normally say, do it, it's like the reverse. When you normally
just write a קנין kinyan in a שטר shtar and whatever, we
say basically, maybe here you're trying to actually do a מתנת בריא
matnas bari and a מתנת בריא לאחר מיתה, matnas bari le-achar misa,
it's gonna be ineffective. That was our first case. But there's ways
you can make it clear that the point of the קנין kinyan
and the שטר shtar and whatever is not a מתנת בריא matnas
bari but is there to beef up a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas
shechiv mera. You say it in an explicit way, and we're gonna
get the formula in a minute, that it's making it clear that
it's only there to beef up the מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shechiv
mera and not to serve as a מתנת בריא. matnas bari. Okay,
and now we're gonna say what that is. Okay. For all those
vegans in the room, I'll say tofu up. Okay. So, the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So יתיב רב נחמן בר יצחק, yasiv Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, so Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak was sitting אחורי דרבא,
achorey de-Rava, in the back of רבא, Rava, ויתיב רבא קמיה דרב
נחמן, ve-yasiv Rava kamei de-Rav Nachman, Rava sitting in front of Rav
Nachman. בעי מיניה, Kaba minei, he asked from him: מי אמר שמואל
שמא לא גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר ואין שטר לאחר מיתה? Mi amar
Shmuel shema lo gamar le-aknosu ella be-shtar ve-ein shtar le-achar misa? How
did שמואל Shmuel say such a thing, that if it was with
a שטר, shtar, then the first thing שמואל Shmuel said, okay, that
if it was a קנין kinyan and a שטר shtar and whatever,
it works like a מתנת בריא matnas bari and it's after death
and it doesn't work? How could you say that? ואמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Ve-amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, we say in the name
of, Rav Yehuda says in the name of שמואל: Shmuel: שכיב מרע
שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים אף על פי שקנו
מידו עמד חוזר. Shechiv mera she-kasav kol nechasav le-acherim af al pi
she-kanu mi-yado amad chozer. If he writes all his נכסים nechasim to
others, even if they performed a קנין, kinyan, right, what we said
over here, even if you did a קנין, kinyan, עמד חוזר. amad
chozer. Now, that's not relevant to us, but what's relevant to us
is בידוע שלא היה קנין אלא מחמת המיתה. bi-yedu'a shelo haya kinyan
ella machmas hamisa. Okay,
that the קנין kinyan was only because of death, and therefore עמד
חוזר. amad chozer. Now, the reason that's relevant is, what does that
have to do with anything? Because what that means is, that if
it were, let me make sure I'm getting this right,
ah, which means is, okay fine, עמד חוזר, amad chozer, but if
he was not עמד, amad, it would be binding. So, here's a
case, a שכיב מרע shechiv mera did a קנין, kinyan, and we
say that that doesn't just make it a,
you know, it just makes it either a stronger or a neutral,
it doesn't affect its status as a שכיב מרע. shechiv mera. שכיב
מרע Shechiv mera did a קנין, kinyan, we're still going to say
עמד חוזר, amad chozer, but we're going to say if he doesn't
עמד, amad, if he dies, it's valid. So, here you see שמואל
Shmuel says a קנין kinyan doesn't affect the status of a מתנת
שכיב מרע. matnas shechiv mera. So, how could the other שמואל Shmuel
say that if you do a קנין, kinyan, it's completely invalidate basically
because it only takes effect after death? Okay, now you have an
answer, right?
Right. So, that's what pushes the רשב"ם Rashbam to say that the
שטר shtar component isn't necessary, because here you're just mentioning a קנין,
kinyan, not a שטר. shtar. Okay. Now, because to, but, but of
course it is so disruptive of everything we said before to say
that a שטר, shtar, what?
שכתב כל נכסיו אף על פי שקנו מידו, she-kasav kol nechasav af
al pi she-kanu mi-yado, but it doesn't say that the קנין kinyan
was written in the שטר. shtar. It sounds like that they're, that
they're parallel tracks, right? So, anyway, so that's what leads to the
debate of the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות. Tosfos. Okay. But within תוספות,
Tosfos, we're going to bracket the question that Eli asked, which is
a good one, because we've been saying the whole discussion is when
the קנין kinyan was not only took place but wrote. written explicitly
in the שטר. Shtar. We're going to assume for whatever reason either
that was the case or the גמרא Gemara right now is assuming
some form of a parallel, okay? But the גמרא Gemara is saying
here's שמואל Shmuel talking about a שטר Shtar and a קנין Kinyan
and saying it's valid. So how could the earlier שמואל Shmuel say
that a שטר Shtar with a קנין Kinyan is not valid? It
only takes effect after death and then it's too late. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואחוי ליה בידיה. V-Achvei Lei Be-Yadeih. So this was
what, you know, this was what who was asking?
רבא Rava was saying this. רבא Rava was in front of רב
נחמן Rav Nachman and he was asking רב נחמן Rav Nachman this
question, okay? And רב נחמן Rav Nachman signaled something to רבא, Rava,
you know, ואישתיק V-Ishtik and רבא Rava was silent. כי קם, Ki
Kam, so after רב נחמן Rav Nachman left, אמר ליה רב נחמן
בר יצחק לרבא, Amar Lei Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak L-Rava, what did
רב נחמן Rav Nachman say to you? You asked a good question.
It sounds in this case that שמואל Shmuel says a שטר Shtar
with a קנין Kinyan is still effective. How are we saying that
the other שמואל Shmuel says a שטר Shtar with a קנין Kinyan
is not effective? אמר ליה, Amar Lei, במיפש כוחו. Be-Myafses Kocho.
This is a special case. A special case of a שטר Shtar
with a קנין Kinyan that it's clear that you're still operating as
a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv Meira and trying to strengthen it,
rather than shifting tracks and operating as a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari
after death, which wouldn't work. Wait, is it difference between the קנין
Kinyan is written in the שטר? Shtar? We just discussed that a
minute ago. Yes, but somehow we're bracketing that right now. I don't
know why. That's what leads to a whole debate of רשב"ם Rashbam
and תוספות, Tosafot, okay? But either one,
either answer is not fully satisfying. But let's bracket it for now.
So היכי דמי מיפש כוחו? Heichi Dami Myafses Kocho? What would be
the way to make it explicit that you're just doing this קנין
Kinyan and שטר Shtar to strengthen the מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv
Meira but not to operate on a different track? אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, here's what you write in the שטר: Shtar: קנינא
מיניה, Kanina Mineih, so the שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira said this and
this and this to us, and we the עדים Edim did a
קנין Kinyan with him, מוסיף אמתנתא
דא. Mosif A-Matnata Da. The keyword here is מוסיף. Mosif. In addition
to this gift of the שכיב מרע, Shchiv Meira, which is totally
valid by itself and didn't need our קנין, Kinyan, okay? And we're
not trying to make it anything else, it's a מתנת שכיב מרע,
Matnas Shchiv Meira, we added this extra קנין Kinyan just for fun,
okay? Just to make it stronger. So if you make it clear
that the קנין Kinyan is being added to strengthen, then he says,
then I would agree to רבא. Rava. So actually it's very interesting,
right? I think the easiest way to conceptualize it is you did
all this stuff that makes it sound like such a classic קנין,
Kinyan, the שטר, Shtar, a קנין, Kinyan, the קנין Kinyan was in
the שטר. Shtar. Which track are you riding on? רבא Rava says
you're staying on the שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira track, but you're beefing
it up. We're doing all the stuff as a way of showing
I can't be חוזר. Chozer. שמואל Shmuel says no, this to me
looks like a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari and it looks to me
so you're on the מתנת ברי Matnas Bari track, but a מתנת
ברי Matnas Bari that you think is going to take effect after
death, so the train gets derailed. It's on the מתנת ברי Matnas
Bari track and it doesn't work. Okay, that's what שמואל Shmuel classically
says because okay, but I can get you on רבא's Rava's track,
if you're explicit that the reason you're doing the קנין Kinyan and
whatever in the שטר Shtar is just as a way of strengthening
the מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas Shchiv Meira, then I would agree to
רבא. Rava. But if you're not explicit about that, I'm going to
interpret this as a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari that you're trying to
have take effect after death and therefore it's going to fail. Okay?
So it's nothing. It's not a שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira and it's
not a מתנת ברי, Matnas Bari, right? It's a failed מתנת ברי
Matnas Bari and it doesn't take effect and everything goes back to
the ירושה. Yerusha. Exactly. Okay, now, but both of you did pick
up that the case we asked from was a case where it
was a קנין Kinyan and a שטר Shtar but not a קנין
Kinyan written in the שטר. Shtar. Okay, so that leads to that
complication. But for now we're just going to assume like תוספות, Tosafot,
that effectively all the cases we're talking about are קנין Kinyan written
in a שטר. Shtar. That lead, that combination of the two, not
just that both are happening, but they're being incorporated into one another,
leads to these questions. I just want to know about backtrack and
bits of things again.
Okay, אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, okay we just did that.
פשיטא, Pshita, כתב לזה וכתב לזה. Katav L-Zeh V-Katav L-Zeh.
Now, okay, so that was very complicated. So we got through the
woods there. Now we're going to go back on some things that
we said before and some nice little summary statements again about מתנת
שכיב מרע. Matnas Shchiv Meira. Okay, פשיטא, Pshita, it's obvious, כתב לזה
וכתב לזה, Katav L-Zeh V-Katav L-Zeh,
so first person wrote my final will and testament and gave it
all to Charlie and then I wrote my final will and testament
and gave it all to Gloria. Okay, so that we know the
answer to this already, but now we're recapping some things. היינו דכי
אתא רב דימי אמר, Heinu De-Ki Ata Rav Dimi Amar, when רב
דימי Rav Dimi came he said, דאתי קניינא ומבטל דאתי קניינא. De-Asi
Kanina U-Mevatel De-Asi Kanina. Okay, a later will cancels out an earlier
one. That's based on anything that's אמר חוזר, Amar Chozer, you're
חוזר במתנתו, Chozer Be-Matnaso, as long as you were operating in the
מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv Meira category. It was either כולה Kula
or it was מצוה מחמת מיתה, Metzaveh Mechamas Misah, then you're fine.
Okay,
כתב וזיכה לזה וכתב וזיכה לזה. Katav V-Zichah L-Zeh V-Katav V-Zichah L-Zeh.
So let's say, however, you did two things, right? Now we're getting
back into the combo. You wrote it all to one person with
a זיכוי. Zikui. Now what does זיכוי Zikui mean? Not the virus.
זיכוי Zikui could mean one of two things.
says it means you handed over the שטר, shtar, okay? תוספות Tosfos
says, of course he handed over the שטר, shtar, that was true
in the first case. A דייתקי diatiki wouldn't even be discussed if
you didn't hand it over, right? Remember the earlier משנה mishna I
quoted to you before? It's completely ineffective as a will if it's
not handed over. So even the first case it had it was
handed over. So says no, we're going back to the types of
things we were discussing earlier. Not only did you go ahead and
write the שטר shtar and hand it over, you did it with
a קנין. kinyan. So now it's similar to this question of when
you've done it with a קנין, kinyan, okay, you've done a קנין,
kinyan, you've done a שטר, shtar, so it sounds like what we
sort of were just discussing. And maybe you didn't do the קנין
kinyan in the שטר, shtar, maybe you did it parallel to the
שטר, shtar, okay, and now what we're asking is, can you now
maybe the effect of doing a קנין kinyan with a written שטר
shtar is that it doesn't let a later will override it? Okay?
That's like different than the earlier discussion. In the earlier discussion is
when you get better, is it voided? Here the discussion is, right,
maybe the value of a קנין kinyan written together with a שטר,
shtar, maybe it's not even written in the שטר, shtar, but taking
place together with a שטר, shtar, should prevent you from writing another
another will to void it. That's the question. So let's take a
look. Okay. But it's not clear whether it's written in the שטר
shtar or not. So let's take a look. כתב וזיכה לזה וכתב
וזיכה לזה. Kasav vezika lize vekasav vezika lize. רב אמר ראשון קנה,
Rav amar rishon kana, no big surprise. רב Rav says the first
one takes effect and it can't be voided. Sounds very familiar. It
sounds like what we were talking about before, right, about the שטר
shtar with a קנין kinyan that רב Rav says it's עמד אינו
חוזר. amad eino chozer. So here too, it can't be you can't
give a second will after the first one if the first one
had a קנין. kinyan. ושמואל אמר שני קנה. Ushmuel amar sheini kana.
No, the second one is effective. Okay. So רב
אמר ראשון קנה הרי היא כמתנת ברי. Rav amar rishon kana harei
hi kematnas bari. Okay, it's like a מתנת ברי. matnas bari. Now
that's a little confusing based on how we were sort of saying
it before, right, because it really is a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas
shchiv meira, but the point is the effect of the קנין kinyan
means that it's not retractable. עמד אינו חוזר, Amad eino chozer, which
is exactly what רב Rav said before. ושמואל אמר שני קנה הרי
היא כמתנת שכיב מרע. Ushmuel amar sheini kana harei hi kematnas shchiv
meira. Okay, it's like a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv meira, which
is means that the קנין kinyan does not make it irreversible. Now
it's a little confusing because that's almost exactly the opposite of the
way I conceptualized the debate earlier. Okay, but let's keep on going
with the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara said איפליגו בה חדא
זימנא, Ipligu bah chada zimna, one minute, doesn't this exactly parallel their
earlier debate? במתנת שכיב מרע שכתב בה קנין. Bematnas shchiv meira shekasav
bah kinyan. So here the גמרא Gemara is making the exact comparison.
So how exactly is a דייתקי diatiki and זיקה zika different than
מתנת שכיב מרע שכתב בה קנין? matnas shchiv meira shekasav bah kinyan?
It almost sounds like it's the same thing. So let's see how
the גמרא Gemara explains what the difference is and why they needed
to debate both cases. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
צריכא, Tzricha, you need to say both cases. אי אמר בהא, Ei
amar beha, had you said
that maybe
in only the first case of שכיב מרע שכתב בה קנין, shchiv
meira shekasav bah kinyan, דהא קאמר רב, deha ka'amar Rav, that's where
רב Rav says you can't back out, משום דקנו מיניה, mishum dekanu
minei, you did a קנין. kinyan. Now one minute, we just said
you did a קנין kinyan here too. So תוספות Tosfos says you
see this is why there's so many debates of רשב"ם Rashbam and
תוספות, Tosfos, there's a lot of vague things. תוספות Tosfos says no,
קנו מיניה kanu minei means it's written that you did the קנין.
kinyan. So when it was written in the שטר shtar that you
did the קנין, kinyan, there we would say okay, you can't be
חוזר. chozer. אבל בהא דלא קנו מיניה, Aval beha dela kanu minei,
here that it wasn't written in the שטר, shtar, so אימא מודה
ליה לשמואל, eima moda leh leShmuel, maybe you can be חוזר. chozer.
Okay and now we're finding out that no, according to רב, Rav,
once you did a קנין kinyan with a שטר, shtar, you can't.
So until now we were saying, right, even with a קנין kinyan
you're חוזר, chozer, even with a שטר shtar you're חוזר, chozer, and
with a שטר shtar plus a קנין. kinyan. So now we have
two cases, right, we have שטר shtar plus קנין, kinyan, and we
have שטר shtar plus קנין kinyan plus קנין, kinyan, you know, בשטר,
bishtar, it's written in the שטר. shtar. So here this one רב
Rav said עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer.
Now we're saying even in this case עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino
chozer, okay, which is a חידוש chiddush because we were saying you
needed it all wrapped up together, right? And now we're saying that
no, even just the שטר shtar and the קנין kinyan is enough
for עמד אינו חוזר amad eino chozer for רב. Rav. That's the
extension for this.
Yeah, so that's that is a חידוש, chiddush, okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי אמר בהא, Ei
amar beha, now if he was just in the second case where
it was a קנין kinyan but without it being written, בהא קאמר
שמואל, beha ka'amar Shmuel, that's where שמואל Shmuel would say that you
could be חוזר. chozer. אבל בהך אימא מודה ליה לרב, Aval beha
eima moda leh leRav, but when it's written in the שטר shtar
and it's all coming combined, maybe there he would agree to רב
Rav that you can't be חוזר? chozer? צריכא, Tzricha, you need to
say. Now, I need to pause for a moment because the way
the גמרא Gemara is written, it sounds like the same way for
רב, Rav, the הלכה halacha is really that they're all the same,
right, שטר shtar with right, that
עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. The same way for רב Rav
it's all the same, right, it's sounding like it's all the same
for שמואל, Shmuel, right, whether it's שטר shtar with a קנין kinyan
side by side or שטר shtar with a קנין kinyan written in
it. But it's not the same, because in this case... of the
דייתיקי dyatiki with the קניין, kinyan, שמואל Shmuel said the first one
is effective. The second one, I'm sorry, שמואל Shmuel said
that the second one is effective. Right? What did שמואל Shmuel say?
Second one is effective, okay? שני קנה. sheni kanah. What did שמואל
Shmuel say by a שטר shtar with a קניין kinyan with a
קניין בשטר? kinyan beshtar? What? ייפה כוחו? yipei kocho?
Without ייפה כוחו, yipei kocho, classic שטר shtar plus קניין kinyan with
a קניין בשטר, kinyan beshtar, without explicit ייפה כוחו. yipei kocho. The
first thing we said on the עמוד amud today was שמואל Shmuel
said לא ידענא מאי אדון בה שמא לא גמר להקנותו בשטר ואין
שטר לאחר מיתה lo yadana mai adun bah shema lo gamar leaknoto
beshtar ve'ein shtar le'achar mitah that it was ineffective. You were trying
to do a מתנת בריא matnas bari to take effect after death
and it doesn't work. So actually, תוספות Tosafot says he tries to
switch the גרסא, girsa, but תוספות Tosafot actually says this is the
הלכה halacha for רב, Rav, עמד אינו חוזר amad eino chozer for
both. For שמואל, Shmuel, it's this way. For שמואל Shmuel we would
say, okay, שטר shtar plus קניין kinyan plus קניין בשטר kinyan beshtar
is מתנת בריא לאחר מיתה matnas bari le'achar mitah which means right
which means okay doesn't work. Okay, but that's how we translated it,
right? You're trying to do a מתנת בריא לאחר מיתה. matnas bari
le'achar mitah. שטר shtar plus a קניין kinyan side by side, right,
שמואל'ס Shmuel's just saying that's just classic מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas sh'chiv
mera. No, מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas sh'chiv mera. Okay, which is why
the second one can override the first. They're valid, but it's no
different than a classic מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera and the
second one can override the first.
What, this isn't so simple. Yeah, it
is. Like, forget שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera for a minute. I write
a דייתיקי, dyatiki, I write a I write a will. Yeah. I
can't write a second will that would be מבטל mevatel the first
one? There's no such thing as a will without the שכיב מרע
sh'chiv mera category. You can gift all your property to take effect
a minute before you die, and then you could be voided afterwards,
but that's not the same as a will because that doesn't cover
property that you
take into possession after you write the will. A classic will is
operating in the context of מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas sh'chiv mera. Only?
Yeah.
That's why, that's what Michael asks, how do you do estate planning,
how do you do it when you're not waiting till your last
moment on your deathbed? Okay, but anyway, but here's the basic thing
the גמרא Gemara is saying is, okay, when you try to with
a קניין kinyan alone, עמד חוזר, amad chozer, שטר shtar alone, עמד
חוזר. amad chozer. How about if you combine them? So now we've
said for רב, Rav, whether it's a שטר shtar with a קניין
kinyan written in it or just a שטר shtar and a קניין,
kinyan, either way those are strengthening it, עמד אינו חוזר amad eino
chozer and also אינו חוזר במתנתו. eino chozer bematnaso. Right? Once that's
true, you can't have a later will that overrides it. שמואל Shmuel
is saying, at least this is the way the תוספות Tosafot reads
it, if you wrapped them all together, you were trying to do
a beefed up מתנת בריא לאחר מיתה matnas bari le'achar mitah which
is going to be void. If you were doing them side by
side, then it was just completely meaningless, then it was just basically
a classic מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera and it just operates
the normal way. Without ייפה כוחו yipei kocho otherwise it would be...
Oh, ייפה כוחו, yipei kocho, right. If you were to do, right,
if you were to do שטר shtar plus קניין, kinyan, whatever, plus
קניין בשטר kinyan beshtar with ייפה את כוחו, yipei es kocho, right,
if you had it like all explicit, right, then שמואל Shmuel would
agree to רב, Rav, even שמואל Shmuel would sort of say, obviously
for רב Rav it's that. But even שמואל Shmuel says, so שמואל
Shmuel has like all three possibilities, right, that would probably be עמד
אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. Okay, that would be ייפה כוחו. yipei
kocho. You're right. So there's like three different scenarios. Let's just finish
the דף. daf. Okay. בסורא מתנו הכי. Besura masnu hachi.
That's how they teach this סוגיא sugya in סורא. Sura. בפומבדיתא מתנו
הכי, Bepumbedisa masnu hachi,
but this is how they teach it in פומבדיתא. Pumbedisa. אמר רב
ירמיה בר אבא, Amar Rav Yirmeya bar Abba, שלחו ליה מבי רב
לשמואל, shalechu lei mibei Rav leShmuel, from the house of רב Rav
they sent to שמואל. Shmuel. ילמדנו רבנו, Yelamdenu rabbeinu, let our master
teach us. שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים וקנו מידו מהו? sh'chiv
mera shekasav kol nechasav la'acherim vekanu miyado mahu? Let's say he did
a שטר shtar and a, you did a קניין, kinyan, he doesn't
even mention a שטר shtar here. שלחו ליה, shalechu lei, he sent
back to them, אין אחר קניין כלום. ein achar kinyan klum. Okay?
Once you've done a קניין, kinyan, you can't retract it. Now, does
that mean? So that's like in this way we learned it, that
would only be like with this ייפה כוחו yipei kocho case. So
this is a different version. This version sounds more like that שמואל
Shmuel is saying what we know like consistent with what we know
from רב. Rav. That once you've done some קניין, kinyan, you can't
retract. Of course here it doesn't even mention the שטר. shtar. Oh,
אלא שכתב כל נכסיו. ela shekasav kol nechasav. Oh, כתב, kasav, I'm
sorry. You're right. You're right, you're right, because קניין kinyan we've already
decided, right. So you're basically like probably in this category, okay. It
sounds like it's just the side-by-side. Okay, and according to this version,
when they're just side-by-side, okay,
then that would be, at least according to this version, a classic
case of strengthening a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera and עמד
אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. Okay, אין אחר קניין כלום ein achar
kinyan klum or you can't retract it and do another one. Let's
just read one more sentence. סבר מינה הני מילי לאחר, savar minah
hani mili le'achar,
we thought initially that meant that you can't write another will to
override, אבל לעצמו לא, aval le'atzmo lo, but if he got better...
it wouldn't be retracted. Okay, that makes sense, right? It's more obvious
it should be retracted if you got better than that you could
override it. אמר ליה רב חסדא, amar lei Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda
said no, כי אתא רב הונא מקופי, ki ata Rav Huna mi-Kufi,
פירש peireish בין לעצמו בין
לאחרין, bein l'atzmo bein l'acherin, whether to yourself or to others, if
it is a שטר shtar and a קנין, kinyan, עמד אינו חוזר,
amad eino chozer, and there and אינו חוזר במתנתו. eino chozer b'matnaso.
And anyway according to this version at least שמואל Shmuel would agree
with this to רב. Rav. So according to the other version, שמואל
Shmuel and רב Rav agree in this case. Here, I'll circle the
cases. In the first version they agree, thank you Eli for putting
it on the board, they agree in the case of מייפה כחו,
miyafeh kocho, and according to version number two they also agree in
the case of a שטר shtar plus a קנין, kinyan, that עמד
אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. All right, but a שטר shtar and
a קנין kinyan and a קנין בשטר, kinyan b'shtar, which is the
case we opened up with, that presumably remains this serious debate of
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. All right, we are done for today.
We finished it and it finished us.